<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:lang="en">
  <title>EPIC - User's Guide</title>

  <chapter id="installation">
    <title>Plug-in Installation</title>

    <section id="prerequisites">
      <title>Prerequisites</title>

      <section>
        <title>Eclipse</title>

        <para>Before installing the EPIC plug-in, a recent version of Eclipse
        has to be installed. The minimum requirement is version 3.1 of Eclipse
        for EPIC 'stable' and version 3.2 of Eclipse for EPIC
        'testing'.</para>

        <para>Eclipse comes in two flavors. The <emphasis>SDK</emphasis>
        version contains Java IDE components and is much larger than the
        <emphasis>Platform</emphasis> version. If you only want to use Eclipse
        as a Perl IDE, the Platform version is sufficient. If you are in for
        Perl and Java coding, use the SDK version.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Eclipse does not include a Java Runtime Environment
        (JRE). You will need a 1.4.1 level or higher Java Runtime or Java
        Development Kit (JDK) installed on your machine in order to run
        Eclipse.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Eclipse can be downloaded from <ulink
        url="http://www.eclipse.org">www.eclipse.org</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Perl</title>

        <para>In order to have all EPIC features like Syntax Checking, Source
        Formatting etc., a Perl interpreter is needed. In principle any Perl
        interpreter can be used. To use debugging within Eclipse, Perl version
        5.8.x or 5.6.x is required. For further requirements concerning the
        debugger, see <xref linkend="setting-up-debugger" />.</para>

        <para>Most *nix/Linux installations will provide Perl interpreters out
        of the box.</para>

        <para>Perl for Windows can be downloaded from <ulink
        url="http://www.activestate.com">www.activestate.com</ulink></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Considerations when using Cygwin</title>

        <para>Make sure that the mount command is available and that it is in
        your system path. As mount is a standard component of Cygwin, you
        usually just have to add the cygwin\bin directory to your system
        path.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing EPIC</title>

      <para>The installation is done by using the Eclipse Update Manager. The
      Update Manager connects to an EPIC Update Site
      [http://e-p-i-c.sourceforge.net/updates]. The Update Site can also be
      stored locally if no Internet connection is available and can be
      downloaded from the <ulink url="http://e-p-i-c.sourceforge.net">EPIC
      project page</ulink>.</para>

      <para>After starting Eclipse, select <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Help</guimenu>

          <guisubmenu>Software and Updates</guisubmenu>

          <guimenuitem>Find and Install...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the menu.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/updates_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Find and Install...</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Select <guilabel>Search for new features to install</guilabel> an
      press <guibutton>Next</guibutton>. Press the <guibutton>Add Update
      Site...</guibutton> button for a remote installation via HTTP or the
      <guibutton>Add Local Site...</guibutton> button if the Update Site is
      available locally. When installing EPIC from remote, enter any desired
      <guilabel>Name</guilabel> and the <guilabel>URL</guilabel>
      <userinput>http://e-p-i-c.sf.net/updates</userinput>.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/updates_2.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Add Update Site...</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Tick the newly created site and press the
      <guibutton>Next</guibutton> button. Follow the instructions of the
      install wizard. The warning about the installation of an unsigned
      feature can be ignored. Eclipse has to be restarted after
      installation.</para>

      <para>Now the EPIC installation should be complete.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Uninstalling EPIC</title>

      <para>To tempoarily disable or uninstall the currently active version of
      EPIC, select <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Help</guimenu>

          <guisubmenu>Software and Updates</guisubmenu>

          <guimenuitem>Manage Configuration</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the menu. Expand the tree in the dialog window
      which appears and select the EPIC feature. Click on the option
      <guilabel>Disable</guilabel> in the panel on the right side and restart
      Eclipse when asked. At this point EPIC is disabled, but still present on
      disk. To remove it completely, enter the same dialog again and select
      the previously disabled version of EPIC (you may need to toggle showing
      disabled features in the dialog's toolbar). The option
      <guilabel>Uninstall</guilabel> will now remove the chosen version of
      EPIC completely.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="preferences">
    <title>Setting Up Preferences</title>

    <para>EPIC preferences can be accessed via <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> from the Eclipse Menu.</para>

    <section id="general-preferences">
      <title>General Preferences</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/preferences_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Preferences...</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Click on <guilabel>Perl</guilabel> to open the General
      Preferences page.</para>

      <para>General preferences include the location of the Perl interpreter,
      the option to enable warnings, taint mode and the interval of the source
      validation.</para>

      <para>The validation interval indicates when to start validation after
      the editor becomes idle.</para>

      <para>Apart from the standard interpreter type, the type can be switched
      to <emphasis>Cygwin</emphasis>. In this case the @INC path is mapped to
      be Cygwin compliant.</para>

      <para>The two debugger-related preferences work as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Enable debugger console</guilabel> is only useful if
          you wish to debug EPIC itself and should not be activated otherwise.
          This preference causes a special console to become available while
          debugging Perl scripts. The console shows internal communication
          between EPIC and the Perl debugger backend. To access this console,
          you have to click on the item <guilabel>perl -d</guilabel> in the
          <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> view.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Suspend debugger at first statement</guilabel>
          (active by default) causes the debugger to stop right at the
          beginning of the debugged script, even if there are no breakpoints
          set. If this preference is inactive, then the debugger will not
          suspend until the first breakpoint is hit (or the script finishes
          execution).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>On slower systems it might be useful to disable automatic syntax
        validation. Syntax validation is still possible by using the <keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>

            <keycap>F5</keycap>
          </keycombo> function key.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Code Assist</title>

      <para>On the Code Assist Preference Page the auto completion trigger
      characters are defined. Normally it should not be necessary to change
      these values.</para>

      <para>By default the editor suggests a list of already used variables
      when the characters <userinput>$ @ %</userinput> are typed. To switch
      this feature off, deselect the <guilabel>Inspect Variables</guilabel>
      check box.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/preferences_5.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Code Assist Preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Editor</title>

      <para>These options define the appearance of the Perl Editor, the
      coloring of the Perl source code, and how annotations are
      displayed.</para>

      <para>Smart typing settings allow to switch auto-completion of quotes,
      parenthesis etc. on or off.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/preferences_2.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Editor Preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Source Formatter</title>

      <para>EPIC uses PerlTidy to format source code. The Source Formatter
      Preference allows to specify PerlTidy command line parameters. To get a
      description of available parameters, press the Help key and select
      <guilabel>PerlTidy</guilabel> options from the popup menu.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/preferences_3.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Source Formatter Preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <note>
        <para>In order for PerlTidy to work correctly, the Perl Interpreter
        Preferences have to be setup correctly (see above).</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="task-tags">
      <title>Task Tags</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/preferences_task_tags.gif" format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Task Tags</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>In this section, you can specify a list of keywords that act as
      markers for tasks inside comments in your Perl code, i.e. tags that mark
      the beginning of a task entry.</para>

      <para>By default, the words <literal>TODO</literal> and
      <literal>TASK</literal> mark the beginning of a task.</para>

      <para>Check the <guilabel>Ignore Case</guilabel> option if you want EPIC
      to recognize task tags case-insensitively, e.g. <literal># todo my
      task</literal>.</para>

      <para>If you select <guilabel>Allow whitespace</guilabel>, task tags do
      not need to follow a comment sign (<literal>#</literal>) directly, e.g.
      <literal># TODO my task</literal> instead of having to write
      <literal>#TODO my task</literal>.</para>

      <para>See <xref linkend="todo-markers" /> to see how to use Task Tags in
      the Perl Editor.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Templates</title>

      <para>Templates are a powerful tool to insert pre-defined code snippets
      while working with the Perl Editor.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/preferences_4.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Template Preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>How Templates are use is covered in <xref
      linkend="working-with-editor" />. The Templates Preference page allows
      the creation, import and export of Templates.</para>

      <para>Exported Templates are stored in XML format.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="associating-files">
      <title>Associating Files with the Perl Editor</title>

      <para>Eclipse associates file extensions with editors. If another
      plug-in is installed, the EPIC Perl Editor might not be used as the
      default editor when opening *.pl, *.pm or *.cgi files. To associate
      these file extensions with the Perl Editor, choose <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the Eclipse menu and select <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Workbench</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>File Associations</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>. If the Perl extensions are missing, they can be created
      by pressing the <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button. Select the Perl
      Editor from the list and press the <guibutton>Default</guibutton>
      button.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/file_associations_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>File Associations</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <note>
        <para>Regrettably, there is currently <ulink
        url="http://www.antlr.org">no way</ulink> to associate EPIC with
        script files that do not have any specific extension but instead begin
        with the <literal>#!/usr/bin/perl</literal> line.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CVS Setup</title>

      <para>By default, Eclipse stores Perl files as binary when they are
      added to the CVS repository. To store Perl files as text (ASCII), select
      <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the Eclipse menu and modify the <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Team</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>File Content</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> settings. Add your Perl extensions (pl, pm etc.) by
      pressing the <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button and specify
      <literal>ASCII</literal> in the <guilabel>Contents</guilabel>
      column.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/cvs_file_content_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>CVS File Content</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="setting-up-debugger">
      <title>Setting Up the Debugger</title>

      <para>Setting up the debugger requires two steps: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><link linkend="general-preferences">Define the Perl
            interpreter to use.</link></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Install the PadWalker Perl module.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <note>
        <para>It is possible to use the debugger without installing PadWalker,
        but in this case local variables won't be shown.</para>

        <para>Download the PadWalker module from <ulink
        url="http://www.cpan.org/">CPAN</ulink> (<ulink
        url="http://search.cpan.org/%7Erobin/PadWalker-0.10/">PadWalker
        1.5</ulink>) and install as described in the installation notes or use
        the installation manager provided with your Perl installation (e.g.
        PPM for ActiveState installations).</para>

        <para>Earlier versions of EPIC provided a custom-compiled version of
        PadWalker for ActiveState 5.8.x. This is no longer necessary; you
        should simply use the most recent version of PadWalker distributed by
        ActiveState.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="perl-projects">
    <title>Perl Projects</title>

    <section>
      <title>Creating a Project</title>

      <para>Perl projects are created (like any other project) by selecting
      <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>

          <guisubmenu>New</guisubmenu>

          <guimenuitem>Project...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the Eclipse menu.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/project_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Creating a Project</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Follow the wizard's instructions to create your Perl Project. Perl
      Projects appear with a custom folder icon in the Navigator view:
      <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/project_icon.gif" format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Project Icon</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title id="include-path">Perl Include Path</title>

      <para>To add entries to a project's Perl Include Path (@INC), right
      click on the project icon and select
      <guimenuitem>Properties...</guimenuitem>.</para>

      <para>If non-absolute paths are entered, they are interpreted as
      relative to the project folder. Standard Eclipse variables (e.g.
      <userinput>${project_loc}</userinput>) can also be used.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/include_path_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>@INC Path Settings</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="converting-project">
      <title>Converting an Existing Project</title>

      <para>To add the Perl Nature to an existing project, select the project
      in the Navigator and select <guimenuitem>Add Perl Nature</guimenuitem>
      from the context menu.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/nature_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Change Perl Nature</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>To remove the Perl Nature from a project, select the project and
      select <guimenuitem>Remove Perl Nature</guimenuitem> from the context
      menu.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Recommended Project Layout</title>

      <para>In order to avoid problems with syntax validation (such as
      packages reported missing) and the debugger (such as skipped
      breakpoints), it is best to organize your project according to the
      conventions of the core Perl distribution:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Keep your own modules in dedicated subtrees of your project.
          For example, create a subdirectory <literal>lib</literal> as the
          root of the subtree containing all *.pm files. Note that you can
          have more than one such subtree. For example, you could also create
          <literal>test/lib</literal> to store modules that are only imported
          by test scripts.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add the root directories of your subtrees to the @INC path
          (see <xref linkend="include-path" />). For example, add the entries
          <userinput>lib</userinput> and <userinput>test/lib</userinput>
          there.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Map package names to paths in the subtree (and vice versa).
          For example, store code for the package <literal>Foo::Bar</literal>
          in file <literal>lib/Foo/Bar.pm</literal> and ensure that
          <literal>lib/Foo/Baz.pm</literal> contains only package
          <literal>Foo::Baz</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Store your Perl scripts anywhere you like in the project. For
          example, in subdirectory <literal>bin</literal> or
          <literal>cgi-bin</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To import from a package, <literal>use</literal> it, rather
          than <literal>require</literal> it. For example, <literal>use
          Foo::Bar;</literal> rather than <literal>require
          '../lib/Foo/Bar.pm';</literal></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="eclipse-basics">
    <title>Eclipse Basics</title>

    <section>
      <title>Perspectives</title>

      <para>Each Workbench window contains one or more perspectives. A
      perspective defines the initial set and layout of views in the Workbench
      window. Within the window, each perspective shares the same set of
      editors. Each perspective provides a set of capabilities aimed at
      accomplishing a specific type of task or works with specific types of
      resources. For example, the Java perspective combines views that you
      would commonly use while editing Java source files, while the Debug
      perspective contains the views that you would use while debugging Java
      programs. As you work in the Workbench, you will probably switch
      perspectives frequently.</para>

      <para>Perspectives control what appears in certain menus and toolbars.
      They define visible <emphasis>action sets</emphasis>, which you can
      change to customize a perspective. You can save a perspective that you
      build in this manner, making your own custom perspective that you can
      open again later.</para>

      <para>You can set your Workbench preferences to open perspectives in the
      same window or in a new window.</para>

      <para>The main perspectives for developing Perl applications are:</para>

      <para><inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/perl_perspective_symbol.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Perl Perspective</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> This is the main perspective for coding Perl
      scripts.</para>

      <para><inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/debug_perspective_symbol.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Debug Perspective</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> Provides the main functionality for debugging and
      executing Perl scripts. For details see <xref
      linkend="debug-perspective" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Views</title>

      <para>Views support editors and provide alternative presentations as
      well as ways to navigate the information in your Workbench. For example,
      the Navigator view displays projects and other resources that you are
      working with.</para>

      <para>Views also have their own menus. To open the menu for a view,
      click the icon at the left end of the view's title bar. Some views also
      have their own toolbars. The actions represented by buttons on view
      toolbars only affect the items within that view.</para>

      <para>A view might appear by itself, or stacked with other views in a
      tabbed notebook. You can change the layout of a perspective by opening
      and closing views and by docking them in different positions in the
      Workbench window.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Perspectives</title>

      <section>
        <title>New Perspectives</title>

        <para>There are several ways to open a new perspective within this
        Workbench window:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Using the Open Perspective button <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/Image70_shortcut2.gif"
                             format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>

                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Open Perspective</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </inlinemediaobject> on the shortcut bar.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choosing a perspective from the <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guisubmenu>Open Perspective</guisubmenu>
              </menuchoice> menu.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To open one by using the shortcut bar button:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the Open Perspective button <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/Image70_shortcut2.gif"
                             format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>

                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Open Perspective</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A menu appears showing the same choices as shown on the
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guisubmenu>Open Perspective</guisubmenu>
              </menuchoice> menu. Choose <guimenuitem>Other</guimenuitem> from
            the menu.</para>

            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/Image70_shortcut3.gif"
                             format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>

                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Open Perspective Menu</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the Select Perspective dialog choose
            <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> and click
            <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/Image70_select_pers.gif"
                             format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>

                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Select Perspective</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>

            <para>The Debug perspective is displayed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>There are several other interesting things to take note
            of.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The title of the window now indicates that the Debug
                perspective is in use.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The shortcut bar contains several perspectives, the
                original Resource perspective, the new Debug perspective and a
                few others. The Debug perspective button is pressed in,
                indicating that it is the current perspective.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>To display the full name of the perspective right click
                the perspective bar and check <guimenuitem>Show
                Text</guimenuitem>.</para>

                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/Image70_shortcut4.gif"
                                 format="GIF" />
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Debug Perspective</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the shortcut bar, click on the Resource perspective
            button. The Resource perspective is once again the current
            perspective. Notice that the set of views is different for each of
            the perspectives.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configuring Perspectives</title>

        <para>In addition to configuring the layout of a perspective you can
        also control several other key aspects of a perspective. These
        include:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <guimenu>New</guimenu> menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guisubmenu>Open Perspective</guisubmenu>
              </menuchoice> menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guisubmenu>Show View</guisubmenu>
              </menuchoice> menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Action sets that show up on the toolbar.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Try customizing one of these items.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the shortcut bar click on the Resource
            perspective.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Customize Perspective...</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select the <guilabel>Commands</guilabel> tab.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Check <guilabel>Launch</guilabel> and click
            <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/Image71_pers_customize.gif"
                             format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>

                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Customizing Perspective</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Observe that the toolbar now includes buttons for debug/run
            launching.</para>

            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/Image71_pers_rundebug.gif"
                             format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>

                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Customized Perspective</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>After experimenting with the other options on the Customize
            Perspective dialog, choose <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Reset Perspective</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> to return the perspective to its original
            state.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Saving a User Defined Perspective</title>

        <para>If you have modified a perspective by adding, deleting, or
        moving (docking) views, you can save your changes for future
        use.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Switch to the perspective that you want to save.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Save Perspective As</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Type a new name for the perspective into the
            <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Resetting Perspectives</title>

        <para>To restore a perspective to its original layout:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Expand <guilabel>Workbench</guilabel> and choose
            <guilabel>Perspectives</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>Available perspectives</guilabel> list,
            select the perspective you want to restore.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click <guibutton>Reset</guibutton>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Views</title>

      <section>
        <title>Opening Views</title>

        <para>Perspectives offer pre-defined combinations of views and
        editors. To open a view that is not included in the current
        perspective, select <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

            <guimenuitem>Show View</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice> from the main menu bar.</para>

        <para>You can create <emphasis>fast views</emphasis> to provide a
        shortcut to views that you use often.</para>

        <para>After adding a view to the current perspective, you may wish to
        save your new layout by clicking <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

            <guimenuitem>Save Perspective As</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Moving and Docking Views</title>

        <para>To change the location of a view in the current
        perspective:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Drag the view by its title bar. Do not release the left
            mouse button yet.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>As you move the view around the Workbench, the mouse pointer
            changes to one of the drop cursors shown in the table below. The
            drop cursor indicates where the view will be docked if you release
            the left mouse button. To see the drop cursor change, drag the
            view over the left, right, top, or bottom border of another view
            or editor.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When the view is in the location that you want, relative to
            the view or editor area underneath the drop cursor, release the
            left mouse button.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>(Optional) If you want to save your changes, select
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Save Perspective As</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> from the main menu bar.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Note that a group of stacked views can be dragged using the
            empty space to the right of the view tabs.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="working-with-editor">
    <title>Working with the Perl Editor</title>

    <section>
      <title>Syntax Check</title>

      <para>EPIC performs on the fly syntax check of Perl source files. In
      order for the Syntax Check to work, the Perl Interpreter has to be set
      up correctly (see <xref linkend="preferences" />).</para>

      <para>The Syntax Check is performed after a defined idle period, after
      the user has stopped typing. This idle period can be configured in the
      preferences.</para>

      <para>When an error/warning has been found, the editor displays the
      appropriate icon in the annotation ruler (the gray bar on the left side
      of the editor), underlines the error in the source, and inserts a marker
      into the Problems view.</para>

      <para>A syntax check can be enforced by pressing <keycombo>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>

          <keycap>F5</keycap>
        </keycombo>. It is also triggered automatically by saving a source
      file.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/syntax_check_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Syntax Check</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Explain Errors and Warnings</title>

      <para>In addition to displaying warnings and errors, the editor is
      capable of explaining them in more detail.</para>

      <para>To get an Error/Warning explanation, right-click the Error/Warning
      icon and select <guimenuitem>Explain Errors/Warnings</guimenuitem> from
      the context menu.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explain_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Explain Errors/Warnings popup</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The explanation(s) will be displayed in the <guilabel>Explain
      Errors/Warnings</guilabel> view:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/explain_2.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Explain Errors/Warnings view</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Open Declaration</title>

      <para>Open Declaration allows the user to search for the declaration of
      a specific subroutine or package.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/OpenDeclaration_Menu.gif" format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Open Declaration context menu</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The search first determines what is selected. If no text is
      selected, it attempts to find a subroutine or package name at the
      current cursor position. The search will fail if neither is
      selected.</para>

      <para>Due to the dynamic nature of Perl programs, the search is not
      entirely reliable. For package names and subroutine names qualified by a
      package prefix, an attempt will be made to locate the appropriately
      named module file using the @INC path. For unqualified subroutine names,
      the search will first occur in the current editor and then extend to
      modules referenced by 'use' and (literal) 'require' statements.</para>

      <para>If the declaration is found, it will be highlighted in an existing
      or new editor.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/OpenDeclaration_Found.gif" format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Open Declaration result</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Perldoc</title>

      <para>To retrieve Perldoc information, select a keyword or text and
      choose <guimenuitem>Perldoc</guimenuitem> from the context menu or press
      <keycombo>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>

          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>H</keycap>
        </keycombo>. If nothing is selected, an input dialog will
      appear.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/perldoc_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Perldoc context menu</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The search is performed among built-in Perl functions, FAQs from
      the Perl documentation, and modules on the include path (see <xref
      linkend="include-path" />). If Perldoc entries are found, they are
      displayed inside the <guilabel>Perldoc</guilabel> view.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/perldoc_2.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Perldoc view</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <note>
        <para>Perldoc has to be installed and available in the system PATH,
        otherwise this feature will not work.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Quick Reference</title>

      <para>Apart from Perldoc support, a quick reference feature is
      available. This feature has the advantage that no perldoc has to be
      installed on the system but does not provide as much information as
      perldoc.</para>

      <para>To view the Quick Reference, select a keyword and move the mouse
      pointer over the selection.</para>

      <para>A tooltip with a short description of the keyword should
      appear.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/quick_reference_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Quick Reference</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Code Assist</title>

      <para>Code Assist features try to assist the user during source code
      editing.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The features currently implemented in EPIC may not be fully
        functional but will be improved in the future.</para>
      </note>

      <section>
        <title>Variable Inspection</title>

        <para>When you press one of the auto completion characters
        <userinput>$ @ %</userinput>, the editor displays all defined
        variables in a list. From the list you can select the variable that
        should be inserted in the source code.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="images/variable_inspection_1.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Variable Inspection</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Module Inspection</title>

        <para>The editor tries to display methods available in modules when
        the auto completion characters <userinput>&gt;</userinput> or
        <userinput>:</userinput> are entered.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="images/module_inspection_1.gif" format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Module Inspection</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <note>
          <para>Currently, indirect object invocations are not recognized by
          code assist. This code block will not work:</para>

          <programlisting>$smtp = new Net::SMTP;
$smtp-&gt;[no content assist]</programlisting>

          <para>This one will work:</para>

          <programlisting>$smtp = Net::SMTP-&gt;new();
$smtp-&gt;[content assist]</programlisting>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="todo-markers">
      <title>Task Markers</title>

      <para><emphasis>Task markers</emphasis> are a very convenient way to add
      items to the Eclipse task list. A task marker is generated when a
      <userinput>#TODO any text</userinput> is found in the Perl source code.
      On deletion of the <userinput>#TODO</userinput> comment, the task marker
      is also deleted.</para>

      <para>You can customize the keywords which begin task markers in the
      preferences (see <xref linkend="task-tags" />).</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/todo_markers_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Task Marker</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Templates</title>

      <para>Templates allow for easy insertion of predefined text segments. In
      addition to normal text these segments can also include pre-defined
      variables that are included at runtime as well as variables that are
      specified by the user when the template is inserted.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Defining Templates</title>

        <para>Templates are defined in the EPIC Preferences (<menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

            <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>). To define a new template, press the
        <guibutton>New...</guibutton> button.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/templates_2.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Template Dialog</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>To insert pre-defined variables, press the <guibutton>Insert
        Variable...</guibutton> button.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/templates_3.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Predefined Variables</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>In addition to pre-defined variables, the user can specify
        additional variables (using the syntax
        <userinput>${varname}</userinput>) which can be edited when the
        template is inserted. When the first variable is inserted, variables
        with the same name will automatically be changed.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using Templates</title>

        <para>Templates are invoked by typing some characters and pressing
        <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>Space</keycap>
          </keycombo>.</para>

        <para>Templates matching the typed characters will be displayed in a
        list. A preview is also available.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/templates_1.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Template Selection</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>If the template contains user defined variables the user can
        press the <keycap>TAB</keycap> key to jump to the next variable after
        the template has been inserted.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/templates_4.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>User Variables</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title id="source-formatter">Source Formatter</title>

      <para>EPIC uses PerlTidy for source code formatting (PerlTidy is
      included in the EPIC package).</para>

      <para>To format the source code, select <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Source</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Format</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the Eclipse menu or use <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>Shift</keycap>

          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo>.</para>

      <para>PerlTidy settings can be changed in the <guilabel>Source
      Formatter</guilabel> preference page.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Source formatting might take a while if the source code has a
        lot of lines.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Source Folding</title>

      <para>The editor supports folding of POD comments and
      subroutines.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/source_folding_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Source Folding</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Source folding can be disabled in the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel>
      preference page.</para>

      <note>
        <para>On big files source folding can decrease performance. So if you
        experience slowdowns, disabling source folding might help.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Refactoring</title>

      <section>
        <title>Extract Subroutine</title>

        <para>Extraction of subroutines is supported by the use of the CPAN
        Devel::Refactor module.</para>

        <para>To extract a subroutine, mark the code to extract and select
        <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Refactor</guimenu>

            <guimenuitem>Extract Subroutine</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice> from the popup menu.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="images/extract_subroutine_1.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Extract Subroutine Selection</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>In the popup menu insert the name of the new subroutine and
        press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="images/extract_subroutine_2.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Extract Subroutine Dialog</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The new subroutine will be placed at the end of the Perl script
        (before <literal>__END__</literal> section) and the selection will be
        replaced with the subroutine call.</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="images/extract_subroutine_3.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Extract Subroutine Result</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <note>
          <para>The extraction might not work properly at the moment because
          the Devel::Refactor module is in an early stage of development. With
          upcoming versions of the module, this function should become more
          reliable.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HTML Export</title>

      <para>To export, select <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Source</guimenu>

          <guisubmenu>Export</guisubmenu>

          <guimenuitem>HTML</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the Eclipse menu and specify an output file.</para>

      <para>HTML export settings can be changed in the <guilabel>Source
      Formatter</guilabel> preference page.</para>

      <note>
        <para>For HTML export to work, a working Source Formatter is needed
        (see <xref linkend="source-formatter" />).</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Outline View</title>

      <para>The <guilabel>Outline</guilabel> view displays packages and
      subroutines defined in the edited file. Modules referenced by 'use'
      statements are also shown. When you click on a module or subroutine name
      in the outline, the editor will jump to the appropriate position in the
      source code. When the cursor is moved inside of a subroutine's
      definition, the subroutine will become selected in the outline.</para>

      <para>Subroutines named <literal>new</literal> will get a different
      icon.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/outline_view_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Outline View</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="using-debugger">
    <title>Using the Perl Debugger</title>

    <section>
      <title>Launching Perl Programs</title>

      <para>You may launch your Perl programs from the workbench. Programs may
      be launched in either run or debug mode.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In run mode, the program executes, but may not be suspended or
          examined.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In debug mode, execution may be suspended and resumed,
          variables may be inspected, and expressions may be evaluated.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The environment a Perl program is to be executed in is defined via
      "Launch Configurations". A launch configuration defines</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>if the program is to be executed in a CGI or normal Perl
          environment</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the host the program is to be executed on</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the program to execute</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>execution parameters to pass</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>environment variables</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>configuration data for the web server used to provide the CGI
          framework</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>Launching Perl Programs in Run Mode</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/run_diag.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Run Configurations Dialog</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Run...</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> from the Eclipse menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Within the appearing dialog, select the configuration
            type:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Perl Local: Run a Perl script on the local
                machine</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Perl CGI: Run Perl programs in a CGI environment on the
                local machine</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Perl Remote: Run a Perl script on a remote
                machine</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>and press the New button to create a new launch
            configuration.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Adjust launch configuration attributes. For details see
            <xref linkend="launch-configurations" />.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <guibutton>Run</guibutton> button.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>This executes the program. The program's console output will be
        shown in the console window. For "Perl Local" and "Perl Remote"
        configurations, the console window also accepts keyboard input to be
        passed to the program.</para>

        <para>If you switch to the debug view, you have additional control
        over the execution of the program. For details see <xref
        linkend="debug-view" />.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Re-launching a Perl Program</title>

        <para>The workbench keeps a history of each launched and debugged
        program. To relaunch a program, do one of the following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a previous launch from <guimenu>Run</guimenu> or
            <guimenu>Debug</guimenu> button pull-down menus.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the menu bar, select <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Run History</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> or <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Debug History</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> and select a previous launch from these
            sub-menus.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the Debug view, select a process that you want to
            relaunch, and select <guimenuitem>Relaunch</guimenuitem> from the
            process's pop-up menu.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To relaunch the most recent launch, do one of the
        following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click the <guibutton>Run</guibutton> or
            <guibutton>Debug</guibutton> buttons (without using the button
            pull-down menu).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Run Last Launched</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> (<keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

                <keycap>F11</keycap>
              </keycombo>), or <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Debug Last Launched</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> (<keycap>F11</keycap>) from the workbench menu
            bar.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="launch-configurations">
      <title>Creating Launch Configurations</title>

      <section>
        <title>Perl Local: Running a Perl Script on the Local Machine</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Debug_Local.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Perl Local Dialog</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter the name for the launch configuration in the
            <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>Main</guilabel> tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Project</guilabel> field: select the project
                which contains the script to execute</para>

                <note>
                  <para>Only Perl projects (projects associated with a Perl
                  nature) will be shown. If the project you require is not
                  shown, see <xref linkend="converting-project" /> for adding
                  a Perl nature to your project.</para>
                </note>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>File to execute</guilabel> field: select the
                script to execute</para>

                <note>
                  <para>Only files associated with the Perl editor will be
                  shown. See <xref linkend="associating-files" /> for
                  details.</para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you wish to pass command-line parameters to the script or
            to the Perl interpreter, enter them in the
            <guilabel>Arguments</guilabel> tab.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you wish to modify environment variables for the script,
            enter them in the <guilabel>Environment</guilabel> tab.<note>
                <para>Be careful when removing or overriding the standard
                environment variables. For example, the environment variable
                %SYSTEMROOT% is essential for Perl socket IO to work under
                Windows.</para>
              </note></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Perl CGI: Run Perl Programs in a CGI Environment</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/debug_cgi.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Perl CGI Dialog</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter the name for the launch configuration in the
            <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>Web Server</guilabel> tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>HTML Root Directory</guilabel> field: enter
                the base directory that contains all HTML files or use the
                <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to select the appropriate
                directory.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>HTML Startup File</guilabel> field: enter the
                file name to be shown in the browser after startup or use the
                <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to select this
                file.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>CGI Root Directory</guilabel> field: enter the
                base directory that contains all CGI files or use the
                <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to select the appropriate
                directory.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Extension for CGI files</guilabel> field: this
                is a comma separated list of file extensions (each starting
                with a "." ) used for CGI files in the project.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>Browser</guilabel> tab, there are two
            possible settings:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Select <guilabel>Custom Browser</guilabel>: specify the
                path to the browser executable and add the required command
                line parameters. Use <literal>%1</literal> as a place holder
                for the HTML file to be opened.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Select <guilabel>Default System Browser</guilabel> to
                use the browser defined as default browser by your OS
                preferences.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you wish to modify environment variables for the script,
            enter them in the <guilabel>Environment</guilabel> tab.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you wish to pass command-line parameters to the Perl
            interpreter, enter them in the <guilabel>Arguments</guilabel>
            tab.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Perl Remote: Debug a Perl Script on a Remote Machine</title>

        <para><note>
            <para>This feature is not tested very well and should be
            considered experimental.</para>
          </note>Some points to consider:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You need a Perl interpreter installed on the remote
            host.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>During debugging the remote host connects to the local
            (Eclipse) host using three TCP ports: the debugger port, the
            stdout/stdin port and the stderr port. The debugger port is
            specified statically in the launch configuration (see below). The
            two other ports are picked up from the range 5000-10000. (EPIC
            attempts to reserve these ports in ascending order starting with
            5000.) Make sure that your firewall does not block these required
            connections.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Scripts executed and code shown are from different sources:
            EPIC displays the code present on your local host and executes a
            copy of this code on the remote host. So if you make changes
            within your project please make sure to transfer these changes to
            the remote host (see below for further details).</para>

            <para>This problem gets more significant for code/modules provided
            by your Perl installation. If modules on your local and remote
            host differ, debugging results may be quite meaningless. So try to
            have the same Perl version installed on both hosts and make sure
            all modules you require (which are not part of your Eclipse
            project) are identical.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>@INC path handling: if the include path references
            directories within your project or directories that are linked
            into your projects, EPIC will include these modules in the list of
            files to be copied to the remote host and adjust the @INC-path for
            your remote host accordingly. Overall, it is best to set up
            project-relative @INC paths in the project properties.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/debug_remote.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Perl Remote Dialog</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter the name for the launch configuration in the
            <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>Configuration</guilabel> tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Project</guilabel> field: select the project
                to debug.</para>

                <note>
                  <para>Only Perl projects (projects associated with a Perl
                  nature) will be shown. If the project you require is not
                  shown, see <xref linkend="converting-project" /> for adding
                  a Perl nature to your project.</para>
                </note>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>File to execute</guilabel> field: select the
                Perl file to execute.</para>

                <note>
                  <para>Only files associated with the Perl editor will be
                  shown. See <xref linkend="associating-files" /> for
                  details.</para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Local Host IP</guilabel>: this is the IP-address
            used by the remote host to connect to your local host. In most
            cases the default value is appropriate.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Target Host Project Installation Path</guilabel>:
            the project's location on the remote host. Make sure that your
            Eclipse project can be found at this location.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Port</guilabel>: Port used by the remote debugger
            to connect to the local host.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Create Debug Package</guilabel>: if checked, a ZIP
            file containing the project files to be transfered to the remote
            host is created. This file is stored at the location indicated in
            <guilabel>Debug Package File Path</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <guibutton>Debug</guibutton> button. At this
            point, the local host starts listening for a remote debugger
            connection.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Extract the ZIP file to the location on your remote host
            indicated in <guilabel>Target Host Project Installation
            Path</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Start the script <command>start_epicDB.pl</command> on your
            remote host (it is included in the ZIP archive and thus located in
            the project directory after extraction). This script starts the
            debugger and makes it connect to the local host.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enjoy debugging...</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="breakpoints">
      <title>Breakpoints</title>

      <para>The Perl debugger supports <emphasis>line breakpoints</emphasis>
      and <emphasis>regular expression breakpoints</emphasis>. Both types of
      breakpoints are set on an executable line of a program. If enabled, they
      suspend thread execution before the corresponding line of code is
      executed. Regular expression breakpoints additionally extract the
      regular expression contained in the line of code they are associated
      with and enable you to debug the regular expression within the <link
      linkend="regexp-plugin">RegExp-Plugin</link>.</para>

      <para>The following symbols are used to indicate breakpoints:</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Status</entry>

              <entry>Line Breakpoint</entry>

              <entry>Regular Expression Breakpoint</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Enabled</entry>

              <entry align="center"><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/line_bp_en.gif" format="GIF" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry align="center"><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/rx_bp_en.gif" format="GIF" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Disabled</entry>

              <entry align="center"><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/line_bp_dis.gif" format="GIF" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry align="center"><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/rx_bp_dis.gif" format="GIF" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Registered with debugger</entry>

              <entry align="center"><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/line_bp_inst.gif" format="GIF" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry align="center"><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/rx_bp_inst.gif" format="GIF" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <note>
        <para>Regular Expressions Breakpoints are still in an experimental
        state and will at the moment only work for expressions of the type:
        <literal>Expr1 =~
        <symbol>&lt;delim&gt;</symbol>regexp<symbol>&lt;delim&gt;</symbol><symbol>modifiers</symbol>;</literal>
        Modifiers are ignored.</para>
      </note>

      <section>
        <title>Setting Breakpoints</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the editor area, open the file where you want to add the
            breakpoint with the Perl editor.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Directly to the left of the line where you want to add the
            breakpoint, open the marker bar (vertical ruler) pop-up menu and
            select <guimenuitem>Add Breakpoint</guimenuitem> or
            <guimenuitem>Add RegExp Breakpoint</guimenuitem>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>While the breakpoint is enabled, thread execution suspends
        before that line of code is executed.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Enabling or Disabling Breakpoints</title>

        <para>Open the debug view, open the <link
        linkend="breakpoints-view"><guilabel>Breakpoints</guilabel>
        view</link> and use the check box in front of the break point to
        enable or disable the break point.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Removing Breakpoints</title>

        <para>There are two possible ways for removing a breakpoint:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Right click on the breakpoint symbol in marker the bar
            (vertical ruler) of the editor pop-up menu and select
            <guimenuitem>Remove Breakpoint</guimenuitem>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Open the debug perspective, open the <link
            linkend="breakpoints-view"><guilabel>Breakpoints</guilabel>
            view</link>, right-click the breakpoint you want to remove and
            select <guimenuitem>Remove</guimenuitem>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="debug-perspective">
      <title>Views in the Debug Perspective</title>

      <para>If any of the views described below is not visible, you can open
      it using the <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

          <guisubmenu>Show View</guisubmenu>
        </menuchoice> menu.</para>

      <section id="debug-view">
        <title>Debug View</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Debug_view.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Debug View</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>This view allows you to manage the debugging or running of
        programs in the workbench. It displays the stack frames for the
        suspended program you are debugging. It also displays the process for
        each target you are running.</para>

        <para>If the program is suspended, its stack frames are shown as child
        elements. Clicking on a stack frame takes you to the corresponding
        line in the Perl editor and updates contents of the <link
        linkend="variables-view"><guilabel>Variables</guilabel> view</link>.
        If necessary, a new editor is opened automatically.</para>

        <note>
          <para>EPIC does not currently include support for debugging
          multi-threaded programs.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section id="variables-view">
        <title>Variables View</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/variables_view.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Variables View</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>When a stack frame is selected, you can see the visible
        variables in that stack frame in the <guilabel>Variables</guilabel>
        view. The view shows the value of primitive (scalar) types. Variables
        which point to data structures such as hashes, lists or objects can be
        examined by expanding them to show their members. Variables that are
        references are dereferenced to show the final scalar value or data
        structure pointed to by the reference chain (or an indication of
        cyclic reference).</para>

        <para>Global variables (including Perl internal variables) are marked
        with an <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/global_var.gif" format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> icon, local variables with an
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/local_var.gif" format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> icon.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Customizing the Variables View</title>

          <para>You can customize the presentation with the configuration
          menu:</para>

          <bridgehead>Show Details Pane</bridgehead>

          <para>To show the detail pane select <guilabel>Vertical View
          Orientation</guilabel> or <guilabel>Horizontal View
          Orientation</guilabel>. Select <guilabel>Variables View
          Only</guilabel> to disable it. The details pane shows the value of
          primitive variables (especially useful for string variables).</para>

          <bridgehead>Highlight Updated Variables</bridgehead>

          <para>If you enable this option, the variables whose values have
          changed during the last execution step (since the last suspend) and
          new variables will be highlighted. If a change has occurred inside
          of a complex variable, the variable will be highlighted and the path
          to the changed value will also be indicated using delta
          symbols:</para>

          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="images/var_delta_complex.gif" format="GIF" />
              </imageobject>

              <textobject>
                <phrase>Change Indicators in Variables View</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>

          <para>This makes it possible to see these kinds of changes even if
          variables are collapsed.</para>

          <note>
            <para>This feature requires EPIC to retrieve and remember the
            value of every variable on each suspend. It may be very slow for
            larger programs (e.g. it might take about 20 seconds for a program
            containing data structures with 5000+ values). For this reason,
            the option is disabled by default and should be used with
            care.</para>
          </note>

          <bridgehead>Select Variables to Display</bridgehead>

          <para>The variables view allows to select the following types of
          variables for displaying by checking the corresponding menu
          entry:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Perl Internal Variables: these are variables provided by
              the Perl interpreter like <varname>$_</varname>,
              <varname>@INC</varname> etc.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Global Variables: variables visible from everywhere in
              your program. More precisely, these are the variables from the
              symbol table of the package in which the debugger is suspended
              or from the <literal>main</literal> package (in scripts).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Local Variables: variables declared with the keyword
              <literal>my</literal>, more correctly called "lexical" variables
              in Perl. To show lexical variables, you need to <link
              linkend="setting-up-debugger">install the Perl PadWalker
              module</link>. The PadWalker module has some <link
              linkend="known-problems">problems</link> which influence viewing
              of local variables.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <bridgehead>Show Addresses of Variables</bridgehead>

          <para>By default, EPIC shows the address to which a reference
          variable points, but it does not show the address of each
          non-reference variable. This additional information can be helpful
          when you wish to check which variable is pointed to by a reference.
          When enabled, the address of each variable (including scalar
          variables) will be displayed right before its value.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="breakpoints-view">
        <title>Breakpoints View</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/breakpoint_view.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Breakpoints View</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The <guilabel>Breakpoints</guilabel> view shows all breakpoints
        (see <xref linkend="breakpoints" />), their state and location.</para>

        <para>By selecting one or more breakpoints and invoking the context
        menu, you can enable, disable or remove these breakpoints.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Perl Expression View</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/perl_expr_view.gif"
                         format="GIF" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Perl Expression View</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The <guilabel>Perl Expression View</guilabel> allows you to
        execute any valid Perl code within the current context of the program
        executed in debug mode.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the view (<menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

                <guisubmenu>Open View</guisubmenu>

                <guimenuitem>Other</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>, then <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>EPIC</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Perl Expression View</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enter the code to execute.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/perl_expr_run.gif" format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject> symbol.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Stepping Through the Execution of a Perl Program</title>

      <para>When a thread is suspended, the step controls can be used to step
      through the execution of the program line-by-line. If a breakpoint is
      encountered while performing a step operation, the execution will
      suspend at the breakpoint and the step operation is ended.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Step Over</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a stack frame in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> view.
            The current line of execution in that stack frame is highlighted
            in the editor in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel>
            perspective.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click the <guibutton>Step Over</guibutton> button
            (<inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/step_over.gif" format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>) in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> view
            toolbar, or press the <keycap>F6</keycap> key. The currently
            selected line is executed and suspends on the next executable
            line.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Step Into</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a stack frame in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> view.
            The current line of execution in that stack frame is highlighted
            in the editor in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel>
            perspective.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click the <guibutton>Step Into</guibutton> button
            (<inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/step_into.gif" format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>) in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> view
            toolbar, or press the <keycap>F5</keycap> key. The next expression
            on the currently selected line to be executed is invoked, and
            execution suspends at the next executable line in the method that
            is invoked.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Run to Return</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a stack frame in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> view.
            The current line of execution in that stack frame is highlighted
            in the editor in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel>
            perspective.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click the <guibutton>Run To Return</guibutton> button
            (<inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/step_out.gif" format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>) in the <guilabel>Debug</guilabel> view
            toolbar, or press the <keycap>F7</keycap> key. Execution resumes
            until the next return statement in the current subroutine is
            executed, and execution suspends on the next executable
            line.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="regexp-plugin">
    <title>RegExp Plug-in</title>

    <section>
      <title>Enabling the RegExp View</title>

      <para>To display the <guilabel>RegExp</guilabel> view, select
      <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Window</guimenu>

          <guisubmenu>Show View</guisubmenu>

          <guimenuitem>Other...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the Eclipse menu and select the <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>EPIC</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>RegExp</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> view from the list.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/show_view_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>RegExp View Selection</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using the RegExp Plug-in</title>

      <para>The RegExp plug-in is a small tool to debug regular
      expressions.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/regexp_1.gif"
                       format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>RegExp View</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>To check if a regular expression is valid, press the <guiicon>Run
      <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/run.gif" format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></guiicon> icon. If the regular expression matches
      the text, it will be signaled by a green icon. If the regular expression
      contains brackets, the matching character groups in text will be
      colored.</para>

      <para>Regular expression shortcuts are available via the context
      menu.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Debugging Regular Expressions</title>

      <para>The Single Step feature allows for a step by step inspection of
      the regular expression.</para>

      <para>If no groups <literal>(<symbol>...</symbol>)</literal> are defined
      by the user, the RegExp Plug-in tries to use logical blocks for
      matching, otherwise the already existing groups are used.</para>

      <para>The following buttons are provided:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/debug_stop.gif" format="GIF" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> Reset (clears all color markers)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/debug_forward.gif" format="GIF" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> Step forward</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/debug_back.gif" format="GIF" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> Step backward</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Known Bugs &amp; Problems</title>

    <para>The <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=75859&amp;atid=545274">Bugs</ulink>
    and <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=75859&amp;atid=545277">Feature
    Requests</ulink> trackers on SourceForge contain descriptions of the
    current open issues for EPIC. If you encounter a problem, you can also
    search the <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?forum_id=258688">Help
    forum</ulink> for previous reports and solutions and ask your question
    there.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="references">
    <title>References</title>

    <para>Part of this document is taken from the official Eclipse
    documentation provided by the Eclipse project and IBM.</para>

    <para>EPIC uses the public domain ANTLR 2 library developed by Terence
    Parr and others in the <ulink url="http://www.antlr.org">ANTLR
    project</ulink>.</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
